Welcome back to a push in under 3
minutes. No time for intros. Let's get
into it. To close out this unit, we're
going to talk about politics. Throughout
US history, we've gone through many
political parties. For the guilded age,
the US has settled on the Republicans
and Democrats. Republicans were
strongest in the North, were often
backed by big businesses and industry,
and supported high tariffs along with
gold standard currency. Democrats were
strongest in the South. They often drew
support from farmers and immigrants and
they liked low tariffs and they were
more likely to support something like
free silver as the currency system. The
ironic part here is that these parties
actually had a lot similar to one
another. They both were pro business.
They both avoided major reform. They
both still relied on Civil War loyalty
for votes. And most of all, they both
were horribly corrupt. Let's zoom in on
the corruption. Something called
political machines traded jobs and aid
for votes, especially in immigrant
neighborhoods. Now, they were corrupt,
but they also filled a welfare gap the
government ignored. A good example of
this was Tam Hall in New York City. The
Pendleton Civil Service Act tried to fix
this by creating merit-based federal
jobs. But even with this, distrust in
government still stayed high. And this
is where some agrarian activists will
form the People's Party or rather better
known as the populist movement. Pretty
much this movement will argue that the
government should protect ordinary
people, not corporations. That means
free silver, a graduated income tax, a
regulation on railroads, and a lot more
things will be argued for. A Democratic
leader who championed key populist
ideals is a man named William Jennings
Bryan. He's best known for his famous
cross of gold speech, where he argued
that ordinary Americans shouldn't be
quote crucified upon a cross of gold,
condemning the gold standard, and
calling for free silver to expand the
money supply. Now, this speech is a
little complex to understand, but to
simplify it, all he was really trying to
do is expand money policies to try and
help farmers and laborers. So,
basically, the common citizen. Now, even
though populists won't be elected for
any presidential elections, you will see
their ideas come up again in
progressivism and the New Deal. And why
don't we call it a day there? On the
screen now are AP style questions for
this topic. Pause. Now,
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I hope this unit wasn't too bad and I
will see you in unit 7.